It's wonderful to be here
أنه لأمر رائع أن أكون هنا
to talk about my journey,
للتحدث عن رحلتي،
to talk about the wheelchair
للحديث عن الكرسي المتحرك
and the freedom it has bought me.
والحرية التي إكتسبتها منه
I started using a wheelchair 16 years ago
لقد بدأت باستخدام الكرسي المتحرك منذ 16 عاماً
when an extended illness
عندما أصبت بمرض
changed the way I could access the world.
غيّر طريقة وصولي الى العالم
When I started using the wheelchair,
عندما بدأت باستخدام الكرسي المتحرك،
it was a tremendous new freedom.
أكسبني قدراً هائﻻً من حرية جديدة
I'd seen my life slip away and become restricted.
رأيت الحياة تهرب مني و أصبحت مقيدة.
It was like having an enormous new toy.
وكان إمتلاك الكرسي المتحرك مثل إمتلاك لعبة جديدة كبيرة.
I could whiz around and feel the wind in my face again.
تمكنت من التحرك و اﻹحساس بنسمات الهواء تداعب وجهي من جديد.
Just being out on the street was exhilarating.
كان مجرد تواجدي في الشارع أمرا مبهجا.
But even though I had this newfound joy and freedom,
ولكن حتى مع شعوري بذلك الفرح و تلك الحرية،
people's reaction completely changed towards me.
تغيرت ردة فعل الناس نحوي
It was as if they couldn't see me anymore,
كما لو أنهم لم يعودوا يروني بعد الآن،
as if an invisibility cloak had descended.
أو كما لو أنني متخفية تحت عباءة للتخفي.
They seemed to see me in terms of their assumptions
كانوا ينظرون إلي بعين إفتراضاتهم الشخصية
of what it must be like to be in a wheelchair.
بماهية الشعور لو كنت على كرسي متحرك
When I asked people their associations with the wheelchair,
عندما أسأل الناس عن ما يعنيه الكرسي المتحرك لهم،
they used words like "limitation," "fear,"
فهم يستخدمون كلمات من مثل "تحديد"، "خوف"
"pity" and "restriction."
"شفقة" و "تقييد."
I realized I'd internalized these responses
أدركت أن هذه الأحكام أثرت في داخلياً
and it had changed who I was on a core level.
وغيرتني من الصميم
A part of me had become alienated from myself.
جزء مني أصبح غريبا عني
I was seeing myself not from my perspective,
لم أكن أشاهد نفسي من وجهة نظري الخاصة
but vividly and continuously from the perspective
ولكن بشكل واضح و دائم من وجهة نظر
of other people's responses to me.
الآخرين نحوي.
As a result, I knew I needed to make my own stories
ونتيجة لذلك ، أدركت أنني بحاجة لكتابة قصصي بنفسي
about this experience,
حول هذه التجربة،
new narratives to reclaim my identity.
رواية جديدة ﻷستعيد هويتي
["Finding Freedom: 'By creating our own stories we learn to take the texts of our lives as seriously as we do 'official' narratives.' — Davis 2009, TEDx Women"]
["العثور على الحرية: وذلك بخلق قصصنا الخاصة ، وتعلُّم أن نأخذ نصوص حياتنا بجدية كما نفعل في عندما نروي الحكايات 'الرسمية' " – [ 2009 ديفيس، للسيدات TEDx ]
I started making work
بدأت العمل
that aimed to communicate something
الذي يهدف لإيصال شيء من الشعور
of the joy and freedom I felt when using a wheelchair --
بالمتعة والحرية اللتان أشعر بها عند استخدام الكرسي المتحرك
a power chair -- to negotiate the world.
كرسي القوة -- ﻷخاطب العالم.
I was working to transform these internalized responses,
كنت أعمل على تحويل تلك الانطباعات الداخلية،
to transform the preconceptions that had so shaped
أحول الأفكار المسبقة التي شكلت
my identity when I started using a wheelchair,
هويتي عندما بدأت باستخدام الكرسي المتحرك
by creating unexpected images.
عن طريق خلق صور غير متوقعة.
The wheelchair became an object to paint and play with.
أصبح الكرسي المتحرك أداة للرسم واللعب.
When I literally started leaving
عندما بدأت حرفياً أترك
traces of my joy and freedom,
آثاراً لمرحي وحريتي،
it was exciting to see
كان من المثير أن أرى
the interested and surprised responses from people.
ردود أفعال الناس التي يملؤها الإهتمام والإندهاش
It seemed to open up new perspectives,
حيث يبدو كأن أفقا جديدا قد فُتِح
and therein lay the paradigm shift.
وهنا تكمن النقلة الحقيقية
It showed that an arts practice
التي أظهرت أن ممارسة الفن
can remake one's identity
من الممكن أن تظهر الهوية الشخصية
and transform preconceptions by revisioning the familiar.
وتغير الأفكار المسبقة عن طريق تغيير المألوف.
So when I began to dive, in 2005,
لذلك عندما بدأت الغوص، في عام 2005،
I realized scuba gear extends your range of activity
أدركت أن معدات الغوص توسع نطاق نشاطك
in just the same way as a wheelchair does,
كما يفعل الكرسي المتحرك بالضبط
but the associations attached to scuba gear
ولكن المعنى المرتبط بمعدات الغوص
are ones of excitement and adventure,
هو الإثارة والمغامرة
completely different to people's responses to the wheelchair.
مختلف تماما عن ردة فعل الناس تجاه كرسي متحرك
So I thought, "I wonder what'll happen
ولذلك تساءلت "ماذا يمكن أن يحدث
if I put the two together?" (Laughter) (Applause)
لو جمعت الاثنين معا؟ " (ضحك) (تصفيق)
And the underwater wheelchair that has resulted
وقد نتج عن ذلك الكرسي المتحرك تحت الماء
has taken me on the most amazing journey
أخذني في أكثر الرحﻻت متعة
over the last seven years.
على مدى السنوات السبع الماضية
So to give you an idea of what that's like,
ولكي أعطيكم فكرة عن ما يبدو عليه الأمر
I'd like to share with you one of the outcomes
أود أن أشارككم أحد النتائج
from creating this spectacle,
من خلال إنتاج هذا العرض
and show you what an amazing journey it's taken me on.
وأريكم تلك الرحلة المدهشة التي خضتها
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It is the most amazing experience,
إنها أكثر التجارب متعة
beyond most other things I've experienced in life.
أكثر من أي شيء شهدته في الحياه
I literally have the freedom to move
لقد امتلكت حرفياً حرية الحركة
in 360 degrees of space
٣٦٠ درجة من الفضاء
and an ecstatic experience of joy and freedom.
و الشعور بالنشوة والمرح والحرية
And the incredibly unexpected thing
والشيء الغير متوقع
is that other people seem to see and feel that too.
أن الأشخاص الذين يشاهدون ذلك يتملكهم الشعور ذاته
Their eyes literally light up,
يظهر ذلك البريق في أعينهم
and they say things like, "I want one of those,"
ويقولون أشياء مثل :"نريد مثلها،"
or, "If you can do that, I can do anything."
أو، "إذا أمكنك القيام بذلك، أنا أستطيع تحقيق أي شيء."
And I'm thinking, it's because in that moment
وأنا أعتقد، ﻷنه في تلك اللحظة
of them seeing an object
التي يرون فيها شيئاً ما
they have no frame of reference for,
لا يملكون أي صورة مسبقة له،
or so transcends the frames of reference
أو أنه قد تجاوز كل الأفكار المسبقة لديهم
they have with the wheelchair,
عن الكرسي المتحرك،
they have to think in a completely new way.
وأن عليهم التفكير بطريقة مختلفة كليا
And I think that moment of completely new thought
وأنا أعتقد أن تلك اللحظة حين تتولد الفكرة الجديدة
perhaps creates a freedom
ربما تخلق حرية
that spreads to the rest of other people's lives.
تنتشر وتعم حياة أناس آخرين
For me, this means that they're seeing
بالنسبة لي، هذا يعني أنهم يدركون
the value of difference,
قيمة الاختلاف،
the joy it brings
والسعادة التي يجلبها
when instead of focusing on loss or limitation,
عندما لا نركز على الخسارة و المحدودية
we see and discover the power and joy
نرى و نكتشف القوة والسعادة
of seeing the world from exciting new perspectives.
في رؤية العالم من منظور جديد و مثير
For me, the wheelchair becomes
بالنسبة لي، أصبح الكرسي المتحرك
a vehicle for transformation.
مركبة للتحول
In fact, I now call the underwater wheelchair "Portal,"
في الحقيقة اﻵن أدعو الكرسي المتحرك تحت الماء "البوابة"
because it's literally pushed me through
لأنني حرفياً عبرت من خلاله
into a new way of being,
لطريق جديد في العيش،
into new dimensions and into a new level of consciousness.
لأبعاد جديدة ، وإلى مستوى جديد من الوعي
And the other thing is,
والشيء الآخر،
that because nobody's seen or heard
لأنه لم يسبق لأحد أن رأى أو سمع
of an underwater wheelchair before,
بكرسي متحرك تحت الماء من قبل،
and creating this spectacle is about creating
وعمل هذا العرض هو من أجل إنشاء
new ways of seeing, being and knowing,
طرق جديدة للرؤية والعيش والمعرفة،
now you have this concept in your mind.
الآن لديكم هذا المفهوم في عقولكم
You're all part of the artwork too.
جميعكم جزء من هذا العمل الفني أيضاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)